foreign
uh
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to episode 63 of
the ask abidjit show
as you know today i'm gonna be taking
questions uh taking questions that you
have asked in the comments tomorrow i'll
be doing a live chat show so today we
will take questions from the comments
now before i do that let me greet you
all who all is there i can see karan
ojaswa
kite house aman arora mani sharma
anuj
blitz park murali
and many more people good evening good
day all of you so great to be with you
all
right
so let us begin with the questions shall
we
let me go into the questions and let's
begin with question number one
this is two questions in one
one by akshay and one by
henry
who is the greatest indian king in terms
of territory and the other question is
in your opinion what was the greatest
dynasty
in all of india's history and how can
modern india learn from it to become
more powerful
yeah good questions
so the greatest indian king in terms of
territory i would imagine it would be
one of
a few few kings
uh i think chandragupta maurya the
mauryan dynasty had a huge uh
amount of territory under one it was
consolidated under them
so i would say it would be chandragupta
maurya or ashok one of these two
then you also had kanishka the great who
also had an immense amount of territory
that he had conquered much of northern
india
afghanistan pakistan and also
a large uh
a large portion of central asia his
territory included
uh it went all the way to the rlc and
the caspian sea so let's take a look at
what it looks like
let me share my screen
and we will go to google maps
okay let me
take this away the question
all right this is the map of india
so
when you talk about the uh territory of
the mauryan empire it included almost
the entire indian subcontinent
which includes afghanistan and pakistan
much much of afghanistan and certainly
all of pakistan so that was the mauryan
territory when it comes to kanishka
his territory extended all the way to
the caspian sea which if you see it's
here
and the rlc which is here so that is an
enormous amount of territory it also
included significant portions
of the xinjiang presentation region of
china
so it was an enormous territory that
kaneshka had conquered
with
military conquest
so that is kanishka's territory now when
it comes to somebody like lalita mukta
peda he also conquered significant
portions of central asia
so he also had a very large territory
uh
and then we cannot forget the cholas who
conquered
essentially the entirety of southeast
asia
so southeast asia is all the way up to
the philippines
it includes indonesia malaysia
singapore which is tiny thailand
cambodia vietnam
laos myanmar of course sri lanka and all
the way to the philippines
so that's how large the chola empire was
so these were some of the greatest
indian empires or or in terms of
territory because
the correct way i mean if you ask who is
the greatest in terms of territory the
measure is
territory how much
territory did they conquer
so these are some of the indian kings or
empires that have the greatest amount of
territory under their dominion right
so
and and the other question is
in your opinion which is the great which
was the greatest dynasty in all of
india's history and what can modern
india learn from it to become more
powerful
uh i the dynasties i just mentioned the
the mauryans
uh the kushans under kanishka uh then uh
lalitha mukta and the cholas etc so
these are some of the greatest dynasties
in terms of territory
in all of indian history so if you use
territory as a measure of greatness then
these are the dynasties that were the
greatest
which is the modern definition today who
conquered the most who had
the most amount of territory under his
or her control that is the definition
the modern definition
so from that you would say that these
four four or so dynasties are the
greatest what can india learn from it
well what can india learn from it to be
more powerful
you have to invest in your military in
your hard power they did not conquer the
world
through love
they did not conquer these vast
territories through love and peace and
brotherly feelings and all that it was
hard power hard
military power that
that was able to
that was the driving force behind these
conquests
right
and because they conquered so much
territory they were able to spread
indian culture and civilization that far
so
it was actually a force of for good
because indian culture indian territory
i mean indian culture and civilization
is not
colonial
in its mindset it is not extractive
indian kings even when they conquered
foreign countries never extracted wealth
out of them they never imposed their
culture by force on anybody they never
massacred anyone so this was a force for
good
so hard power
translated itself into a force for good
in this case
unlike what happened during the european
colonization which ruined the world
so the simple thing that india can learn
from this is that we need to invest in
hard power forget about this obsession
this fetish for soft power
invest in hard power which is military
power and economic power that's all that
matters in the long run
so good question to start off with
okay question number two
this is by h2 what's your take on the
recent ongoing excavations surrounding
tamil nadu will it lead to the discovery
of a contemporary civilization this
civilization purunai river civilization
to the indus valley civilization and may
it prove the dravidians concept
and potentially rewriting our indian
history and origin as you know it
look
these excavations in shiva galai kiladi
etc various other places in southern
india they are certainly going to
rewrite
indian history they're going to shed a
whole new kind of light on india's
history
so that is certainly going to happen
it's not going to throw up some new
civilization the problem with the media
today is that every time they find a new
archaeological site they call it a new
civilization civilization so killer d
civilization why guy river civilization
uh puruna civilization every single new
archaeological site is construed as a
new civilization which is so stupid
there's only one civilization in the
indian subcontinent
it's more than 10 000 years old it's the
indian civilization north south east
west was all part of it
and there is no such thing as aryans and
dravidians we are the same people
we live in vastly different regions of
the subcontinent and that's why over the
generations over hundreds of generations
we have kind of because we stayed in
these regions we kind of
picked up different appearances some are
fairer some are darker and so on and so
forth the different linguistic
differences because
the world was not not like it is today
today you can go to chennai you can go
to uh guwahati you can go to ladakh
in in a matter of hours you can just hop
onto a plane and go anywhere you want
there is so much interconnectivity today
the the
speed of travel is so fast the speed of
communications is so fast
2 000 years ago 3000 years ago
it was not that way
even though it is a single civilization
single culture you have because of the
enormous distances involved you had so
many local manifestations very diverse
very plural manifestations of the same
culture everywhere and that's why it
looks like south india is different from
north india and east is different from
west and all that nonsense which is not
the case we are the same people with the
same culture the same genetics the same
genetic origin and so on so there is no
such thing as aryans and dravidians and
this has been proven so many times
through genetic studies and so and all
that
so it's not going to prove that there
was a separate dravidian race and a
separate aryan race and all that
nonsense it's going to disprove all that
we're already finding evidence of brahmi
script
all the way down south in southern india
right
now now the the the uh
the historians are trying to portray
that as tamil brahmi what on earth is
tamil brahmi
it's just brahmi brahmi is a script
it's not a language you can't give it
the name of a language it's a script
that devanagari script is doesn't have
sanskrit dev nagari and marathi
devanagari and hindi divina variance
it's just a script it's just the devna
script
similarly brahmi is just brahmi there's
not tamil brahmi and some other brahmi
so these are the artificial distortions
that are being imposed upon these things
and that's why people keep on believing
that there are differences there are no
differences i would certainly expect
that we will find lots of more data lots
of more archaeological sites throughout
india east west
north south center everywhere in
southern india we'll find lots of stuff
we have just begun scratching the
surface
so these uh we will find lots of new
archaeological sites that will certainly
be contemporaneous with the indus valley
uh civilization so-called indus valley
or saraswati civilization certainly it
will be contemporaneous with that there
is no doubt about it it's going to
rewrite indian history in the sense that
we will start to realize that just as
india is an enormous networked
civilization today it was the same
several thousand years ago as well the
only difference was that the speed of
travel wasn't there the speed of
communication wasn't there and yet it
was just one civilization
right so that's what we're going to find
it was all interconnected it was the
same civilization and we had the same
culture everywhere that is how indian
history is going to be rewritten because
right now we feel that india is a
is is uh
is divided
into north indians and south indians
essentially and also east west all that
nonsense so there is all going to
disappear slowly
as we find more data from new
archaeology archaeological sites so that
is what's going to happen
next question is by avinash avinash says
where is the center of the observable
universe the good question so let's take
a look at uh
depictions of the observable universe
we
see
let me put it on the screen
i have done a simple google search for
observable universe and let's take a
look at the images
so this is a good representation of the
observable universe all right this is
the observable universe the actual
universe may be much much much larger
than that
but uh
the observable universe has a
diameter of approximately 93 billion
light years which gives it a radius of
half of that which is 46.5 billion light
years
and that's how far we can see
and much of it is going out going beyond
our observable horizon because of the
expansion of the universe but this is
the observable universe and we are at
the very center of that
because we can only see that far in all
directions
so the center
of the observable universe as far as i
am concerned
you see
as far as i am concerned the center of
the observable universe is me
and as far as avinash
is concerned
the center of the observable universe is
him wherever he is right now
and all of you my viewers as far as you
are concerned
the center of the observable universe is
where you are at this very moment
you are the center of the observable
universe
from your perspective from your
reference frame and for me this here
right now
is the center of the observable universe
that is how it goes
next question is by akash
do we know how supermassive black holes
come into existence
stellar black holes form in a supernova
explosion but how do supermassive black
holes form
so most black holes
stellar mass black holes form
in supernova explosions not always there
are certain cases in which if a star is
massive enough it never goes supernova
it just winks out of existence and goes
black
or goes you know it stops emitting light
it collapses straight into a black hole
without ever going supernova so that
also is uh is believed to happen there
are mechanisms by which that can happen
but
when you talk about stellar mass black
holes
it's always something that results from
the death of a star
so so that's the mechanism
now what about supermassive black holes
so almost every galaxy that we know
happens to have an enormous supermassive
black hole at its center so that is
where a
significant amount of the mass of the
galaxy is concentrated a supermassive
black hole typically has a mass of over
a million solar masses
right so the question is how did these
supermassive black holes come into
existence and why do they exist at the
center of almost every galaxy
so it is believed
that in the extremely early universe
very early universe just a fraction of a
second after the big bang took place the
very early universe was very small
it was very small all of the energy and
mass of the universe was concentrated in
a very small
area a very small volume rather right
and the density of of
energy it was just energy at the time it
was incredibly high incredibly high
energy density and in this very early
universe you had quantum fluctuations
happening quantum fluctuations are
is a quantum mechanical phenomenon if
you look at the vacuum of space today
you will find that it's not empty you
have particle anti-particle pairs
coming into existence and will be
winking out of existence all the time so
the emptiness of space is actually an
illusion it's all teeming with these
particle antibiotic pairs these are
called quantum this is what comes out of
quantum field theory and the same
phenomenon was there in the very early
universe
you had these quantum fluctuations
and because of the incredible density
energy density of the universe some of
these quantum rather many of these
quantum fluctuations would have possibly
caused over densities
of space
in space which means that the density in
some regions of space in that time in
that very small universe
would have been so large that they would
have formed microscopic black holes
right so it is expected it is believed
that in the very early universe
just
fractions of seconds after the big bang
happened you would have had in a massive
amount of
micro black holes that were produced at
the time
microscopic black holes or primordial
black holes and it is believed that
these
ancient primordial microscopic black
holes would have formed the seeds
of future galaxies
so that's what is one of the mechanisms
by which
these
over densities of mass
black holes primordial black holes would
have as the universe expanded formed the
seeds around which future galaxies would
have formed
and these primordial microscopic black
holes over time would have grown into
what are now supermassive black holes so
that is one of the um
that is one of the mainstream uh
theories
about the origin of supermassive black
holes so the universe is about 13.7 13.8
billion years old so
most likely in that time these ancient
primordial black holes accrued mass
right they are created a lot of mass and
slowly they grew over time and became
larger and larger and lots of other
visible mass
gathered around them
and eventually became galaxies and these
black holes at the center they grew more
and more massive and today they are what
we call supermassive black holes we also
have ultra massive black holes that we
can't explain how they formed but these
mysteries do exist and do persist but as
far as supermassive black holes are
concerned this mechanism that i just
described seems to be a good mechanism
for how they came into existence and how
they grew over the billions of years to
the size that we to the sizes that we
observe today
so i hope that answered the question
raghav says can trump again become the
president in 2024 i find it extremely
unlikely
let me see how old mr trump is
let's take a look at mr trump's age
okay i don't know what happened there
let's see what his age is
he is 75 years old and this is the end
of 2021 as of today
so
in another three years he will be 78
years old you think it is
it makes sense for somebody to run for
president at the age of 77 78 i don't
think it makes a lot of sense people
typically want somebody who's somewhat
younger at least in his or her 60s right
if not younger i mean obama was in his
40s when he became president he is one
of the youngest presidents in the united
states typically politicians who succeed
at that level are in their 50s or 60s
typically
mr biden
is much older how old is mr biden let me
see
the biden is 79 years old at the time
and you can see that his puff he is no
longer as active and as
well
as as vigorous as he would have been
let's say 10 years ago
so it always helps if a person is a
little younger because the presidency of
the united states is a very stressful
job
so mr trump is going to be
is going to be 77 or 78 when the next
election season comes in so that itself
is going to make it hard for him
to campaign that age maybe he's strong
enough vigorous enough but people want
someone younger typically right
and if there are younger candidates then
that may work against him it may work in
the younger candidate's favor and
secondly the the larger problem is that
the american political establishment
sees mr trump
and his presidency as a huge mistake he
was an outsider he is not a career
politician he's an extremely enormous
enormously successful businessman that's
what he was
and
like i have said in the past
money doesn't buy you power but power
can buy you money but in the case of mr
trump
he was able to
become the president because he was
popular
and
so i think the american establishment
sees that as a mistake they want
somebody who is part of the
establishment they don't want any
outsiders to ever knock down the door
and barge in the way it happened with mr
trump so i think they will ensure
that somebody like mr trump is not able
to succeed
in the future because it harms their
long-term political interests and
agendas on either side outside of the
political divide whether you're
democrats or republicans like when mr
trump was impeached during the
near the end of his presidency
many republicans voted in favor of this
impeachment even though they are par
they were members of his party so it
shows that there is a there was a great
deal of
of dissatisfaction
with mr trump
and his success even within his own
party so i think it is extremely
unlikely that he will succeed again
uh he may run for presidency in 24 but
his own party
may
scupper his chances so that's what i
imagine will happen but let's see how it
goes i i think it's quite unlikely
that he will succeed
okay rajesh says what is the millennium
challenge corporation and is it
beneficial for a country like nepal i
think the mcc is some u.s
is it a ngo or something it is some kind
of
it's not exactly an ngo but it is in
some way associated with the u.s
government it is a funding agency of
sorts of sorts that provides funding to
certain projects in some countries
provided they meet certain requirements
certain political requirements the
country has to be democratic
and it has to have respect for human
rights and it has to share values with
the us and that sort of nonsense
and if you
conform to their requirements then they
will give you some funds
for undertaking certain projects in your
country development projects i think it
is funding some
electric electricity project or
something in nepal
from kathmandu it it goes through
kathmandu to somewhere else and so on so
it is something that is it's like a
carrot and stick kind of thing you do
certain things you make certain changes
in your country and we will give you
this carrot you know a few million
dollars or something like that to
undertake a certain
project or so so that is one way of
that is one of the ways in which the us
increases its influence in countries by
giving these financial stops
and so on so the money is provided to
the government and then it can be used
in whatever way the government sees best
and the output the end result should be
that the project
should be more or less complete you know
that sort of thing so you could you
could construe that as a kind of a bribe
in a sense
so it i think the us is using these
means to uh
retain some influence in nepal because
as we know the chinese influence is
growing significantly in nepal what
happened was that nepal was once a hindu
monarchy until the 1990s
then
uh
i think it was mr rajiv gandhi's
government which which started this uh
this process of uh
of undermining the hindu monarchy of
nepal
uh the maoist terrorist insurgents
whatever you want to call them were
encouraged they were given uh given
assistance
clandestinely from india i think it's
all very well documented it's not me who
is saying this it is a raw it is a
former royal chief who had said that
let's take a look at that let's let's
take a look at that
let's see what was said see it's it is
in dna india
the indian r and aw throughout the
monarchy in nepal during mr rajiv
gandhi's time rajiv gandhi threw out
hindu monarch in nepal and so on so i
think it is all well known by now
that it was mr gandhi the congress party
which ensured that the hindu monarchy of
nepal was destroyed
and
the maoists the communists the marxists
they came into power
that's what happened
and as a result of that
nepal is now under a great deal of
turmoil the culture is under a
significant amount of attack
missionaries are having a free reign in
the country and the chinese communist
party
has
gained a great amount of influence in
nepalese politics today
so i don't know what was the objective
that mr rajiv gandhi was trying to
achieve but it ended up harming
the national interest of nepal and the
national interests of india
so
i think the americans are trying to
offset that by by
by offering these incentives and all
that to the nepalese
to retain some kind of influence in
nepal so is it beneficial for a country
like nepal i
well it all depends on how the nepalese
approach this
i think there was some concern about
the contract
between the mcc and the country of nepal
being such that it will
supersede or override nepalese laws and
constitution that was one of the
concerns that has been clarified to some
extent but questions still persist
so i think it's never
really beneficial for a country like
nepal in the long run
the americans are not doing this to help
the nepalese they're doing it
to further their geopolitical interests
but
the question is what is better the
chinese influence or american influence
i think american influence on balance
would be better for nepal
than chinese influence we know what
china seeks it seeks to simply use and
throw other countries the way it has
been doing everywhere
and nepal is if the people of nepal
think that chinese china is that big
brother they're going to help nepal come
on man why who are you kidding
so i think overall
on balance american influence is better
than chinese influence at least
for now for the short term in nepal in
the long run nepal has to rise again as
a culture
as a country
hopefully one day the entire indian
subcontinent will be integrated again
under indian civilization not some
foreign civilization or foreign culture
in the future long-term project but as
of now now nepal should ensure that it
is not
used
as a pawn
on the geopolitical chess board by peop
by countries who don't really care for
its
long-term interests
so that's what i can say about that
amandeep singh
asks do humans naturally follow polygamy
or monogamy
see if you look at human history
there's always been roughly a one-to-one
ratio of males and females
right when a child is born there's
always a 50-50 chance it's a boy or a
girl and that is how it has
statistically always been
so when you have a one-to-one ratio of
males and females it is
it is
but natural
that monogamy would be preferred to
polygamy because i mean
how can
it be a standard practice for a man to
have multiple wives
when you have only one female
per male in the human population so i
think historically throughout the
history of the
human
species
one would expect that humans have
followed monogamy rather than polygamy
of course in certain cases when when you
had kings and emperors those people
could i suppose
uh
bucked the trend buck the norm and and
because they were so wealthy and
prosperous and they could afford to do
it they could have multiple vibes and
all that but that is i would say
the exception rather than the
norm
so naturally you would you would expect
that humans follow
monogamy not polygamy of course when you
look at a country when you look at the
western world today they have lost their
their cultural moorings
and today you find that people get
divorced all the time people have
multiple partners
quite often
right if you look at a person's uh
lifetime they would typically have
multiple such partners that they either
marry or have relationships with over a
period of time so that is a cultural
thing so in in the western countries
let's take the u.s for instance the
divorce rates are very high people
typically get divorced within three to
five years i would expect i may be wrong
about that but typically it's marriages
don't last very long
uh most children grow up in a single
parent household and all that
youngsters have multiple affairs and all
that so it's become the norm
but that is not polygamy or monogamy
that's something else altogether
it's just a breakdown of the societal
system i would say cultural system and
all that
but at one time
one person typically has only one
relationship going even in the west
today so i think it is
natural for humans to have a single
partner at a given time mostly i think
humans have been monogamous throughout
our most of our history so that's what i
would see this as
harshit says if the no if the knowledge
of the vedas was transferred orally by
ancient priests
through the recital of hymns then how
were historians able to predict the age
of the vedas and confirm its origin to
1500 bce
where is the confirmation
there is no
how were confirmation
able to predict the age of the vedas it
was uh european uh
historians
who tried to fit everything the entire
timeline of human history into the
biblical time frame according to the
bible the world was according to the
biblical worldview the abrahamic
worldview
uh the world was created about four
thousand or so years ago
and there was nothing before that
so how can indian history be five six
seven thousand years old how dare it fit
everything into this short time frame
and that's why people like max miller
etc
they force fitted
the dates of the vedas to around 1500
bce
and also they had to
propagate the rn invasion theory the
iron invasion myth so all that is just
completely arbitrary
there is no confirmation of the date of
the vedas to 1500 bce just because all
the historians today try to create a
consensus and trying to create this
narrative
that the vedas are that old doesn't mean
it's true it's not been proven
there is not a single shred of evidence
that proves that the vedas were written
only around 1500 bce if you look at the
actual contents of the vedas you can see
that they are far older than that far
far older than that i mean
i've spoken about this multiple times
let me say it again in the rig veda the
oldest text that we have in human
literature
the oldest known text in human
literature is the rigveda in which there
are
copious
references to the great mighty river
saraswati it is described as a
mighty mighty powerful river roaring
and the mother of floods roaring loudly
and so on and so forth it's described as
a mighty river
now
geological analysis and data and studies
they show that this river dried out
around 1900 to 1500 bce
which shows you which tells it that the
rig weather could never have been
written around 1500 bce
it would have been written closer to
when this great river was in its prime
and it was last in its prime around 6000
bc
right
so i'm not saying the rig with those
written around 6000 bc but it was
written closer to 6000 bc than to 1500
bc that is for sure that is undeniable
based on the evidence within the text
itself
it's not referring to some mythological
river it's referring to an actual river
and that actual river has been found
today so that argument has gone out of
the window
and still the in making these
baseless claims
and the problem is that these claims are
still treated as the gospel truth
in india's media they are taught as
truth in india's academic system and so
on and that's why people all of us not
me
and not me anymore but most indians
today still believe that there is a
confirmation of the date of the vedas to
around 1500 bce which is not true at all
so uh so historians have not been able
to predict the age of the vedas and
confirm their origin to 1500 bc these
are all
outright blatant lies
is a question by akash
is white skin really superior and makes
a person more beautiful you once said
that in our country dark skin was
rejoiced and probably didn't even matter
much before the british came
considering indian civilization was so
vast and spanned out from ghandar to the
to dravida etc
and hosting a myriad a variety of
complexions and facial features
and no discrimination was observed
towards anyone did this perception start
across the world by the europeans
because they colonized much of the world
at one point
and
the fair skin industry is on the rise
since a lot of people especially females
are mentally colonized into looking fair
and lovely pun intended
is it also one of the causes of the rift
rift between north south fanned by the
politicians of the south and linked with
the rn invasion myth all of this is
certainly interconnected so the first
question is is white skin superior no
it's not superior white skin is actually
a disadvantage if you want to travel the
world and
live in various parts of the world if
you have white skin pale skin
then you are extremely susceptible to
radiation damage
right because the sun the the sun is a
star that gives off all kinds of
radiation much of it is trapped by the
magnetic field of the earth and yet you
have a lot of ultraviolet ultraviolet
rays etc
that
come in
they
they reach the surface of the earth and
they cause
they are potentially dangerous to humans
and that's why we have
uh we have adapted
to evolve uh various skin colors
depending on where we have historically
lived so the people who lived closest to
the equator traditionally
that's typically the people of africa
equatorial africa they have the darkest
skin because they receive the most
amount of radiation from the sun and
people who live closer to the poles they
have
evolved lighter skin colors less melanin
but if you look at the globe
the majority of the globe is regions
where you receive more sunlight and more
radiation and therefore people who have
lighter skin skin paler skin if they
move to such part of the world
the incidence of skin cancer and other
problems rises dramatically australia
has one of the highest rates of skin
cancer in the world because the european
colonizers who live there aren't suited
to that sort of
environment right so that's what you
find so actually i would say that pale
skin is actually a disadvantage
it is not evolutionary great
if you want to travel the world
and in india we have all kinds of skin
complexions ranging from proper pale
pale skin like europeans to almost
african like dark skin
because we it's it's an enormous
subcontinent and people lived in various
environments for long long periods of
time
maybe dozens or maybe even hundreds of
generations
so in india historically there was no
such perception that dark skin or light
skin has any significance on your
personal uh
value of of
of how good or how valuable a human
being you are if you look at ancient
depictions of indians
in cave paintings like ajanta elora etc
you will find people with fair skin
lighter skin people with significantly
dark skin and they are all portrayed as
the same
in it i think in ajantha or elora you
have many depictions of ladies and
people with significantly dark skin then
they are portrayed as being very
beautiful so in india before the uh past
1000 years there never was this
perception that skin color has any
significance on on
on on your personal worth as a human
being
i mean indians
regarded
the greeks as in kind of inferior
lectures right
even the scientists who may have had
lighter skin possibly than the average
indian so indians regarded these people
as inferior because they had they were
not culturally as evolved as indians so
it was all about culture culture was
what made you superior or inferior not
the color of your skin
so historically india had never had this
in the past 1000 years
india was first invaded by the turks who
typically have lighter skin than indians
and then by the europeans the british
who also typically have lighter skin
than indians and it is during these past
1000 years that i think this this
mentality has
crept into the indian psyche that
because these people who conquered us
and subjugated us for a thousand years
they had lighter skin then maybe it
means that lighter skin is superior
maybe it's that way so that false sense
of of this skin color thing has crept
into indian into the indian mind into
the indian psyche over the past thousand
years or so before that it was never
that way
so white skin is in no way superior
i i mean come on skin color has no
bearing on your worth and your value as
an individual
and now uh
so that's what i would say about that
this uh
fair and lovely nonsense the skin color
the skin fair skin industry it it
it's very unfortunate that people try to
lighten their skin color using these
various cosmetic products and all that
and yes it is
one of the causes of the rift between
the north and south which is fanned by
politicians
so the rn invasion myth says that the
aryans were white people
the
original indians are black or browns
dark brown skinned people dravidians
apparently
and therefore people
who live in india today and who have
lighter skin tones are descendants of
arya's they are the invaders of india
they are the descendants of the ones who
subjugated the dravidians and therefore
they are outsiders they are evil
they are not the real indians
and that is something that the iron
innovation theory says and that is what
has been used by politicians in southern
india
to gain votes and stay in power for
decades
they every year i think they garland the
statue of that fellow that bishop
caldwell in in tamil nadu i think
because he is the originator of the
aryan dravidian myth and which has
benefited this politician so greatly so
they garland his statue and honor him
every year for that
for for giving us this lie
so these are the the
the myths that that keep india divided
[Music]
what india is is much deeper than
superficial skin colors
be
india indians are the same people
whatever the skin color is right so that
that's what genetics tells us so we have
to rise above all these lies and that
will happen only when we realize what
the real what the truth is
and i know what comments i'm going to
get every time i say these things i get
lots of comments from certain people not
everybody most people understand this
but some people will always come and
comment please i implore you look at the
actual data and statistics stop being
blind sheep stop believing things
blindly trust your intelligence
learn how to look for information the
information is available publicly the
genetic data and all that
learn how to search for it and look it
up yourself
this is by ching
the question is why is there so much
mediocrity in both my school and college
my classmates are not interested in
science i haven't found even a single
student in my class interested in
physics or cosmology or astronomy or
astrophysics
they are neither ambitious
is this the situation in all this is the
situation in
almost all the sections of my school why
is it so
[Laughter]
a very good question
mediocrity
so what is the definition of the word
mediocre
the word mediocre doesn't mean
the the meaning of this word is average
mediocre means average
so if you look at the average human
being they are going to be average they
will not have any extraordinary
interests
and there is nothing wrong with that
the average person is going to have
average interests and
they will want to have an average
life everybody wants to have an
extraordinary life but most people are
unable unwilling or incapable of putting
in the hard work or dedication and all
that to become extraordinary individuals
and most people are just happy with the
status quo nothing wrong with that there
absolutely nothing wrong with that
there's nothing wrong with a
nine-to-five job there's nothing wrong
wrong with him raising a family and
being being normal nothing wrong with
that
but
that's just how it is
now uh
my classmates are not interested in well
i when i was a kid my customers were
never interested in science i was always
the odd sheep
i've always been different and that's
how it is so if you have interests that
are out of the ordinary then you will
feel certainly always
that everybody is different and they
have no interest in what i have what i
personally am interested in
now one of the reasons for this is that
the the
overall
atmosphere in india is such that
science
is not promoted there are no science
communicators in india there are no
science fiction writers in india the
indian history the i mean india is the
birthplace of science mathematics and
science but this is not taught to us and
therefore we do not regard that as part
of our heritage and so on and so forth
and even if somebody has an interest in
astronomy astrology there's no they
don't know where to get knowledge about
this from where to study this
there are no role models i mean if you
look at the past 50 years of
uh history in india tell me one great
scientist who has come up with a
world-changing invention
or a world-changing discovery in physics
or any in in
chemistry in biology there are some
indians who did that a handful but they
all did it in the west
nothing has come out of india and
therefore the the
the environment
that you need
to promote science
doesn't exist in india
the role models are all bollywood actors
and actresses
right
and
none of them ever speaks about science i
mean maybe one or two may but
maybe they're not alive
or so on so forth so the overall
atmosphere in india the cultural
atmosphere the cultural milieu etc
is such that science is not important
astronomy physics cosmology chemistry
biology these things are not considered
to be important what is important is
that you get an mba or some degree like
that you get a private job
that sort of thing so these are the
reasons
why
there is a significant market
lack of interest in science
so this is what you will find in every
school
in india
north south east west everywhere you
will always have people with the talent
for it with the aptitude for it but they
will not know where to get inspiration
from
so what i would suggest to you chuching
is that
don't be discouraged if you have
interests that are different from those
of other of your colleagues of your
peers it's not a bad thing it means
you're different it means you're special
so find ways of pursuing those interests
maybe you will contribute something
great to the country into the world
so i would encourage you to not be
discouraged and to
follow your interests and do whatever
you think
is is
the right direction for you
all right
okay
did srinivas ramanujan gain his
knowledge from a goddess or a deity as
he was a true devotee of the goddess
namgari
i've heard many times from satguru that
these are concentrated energy forms
and can be used in many different ways
if approached correctly
well i do not have a personal insight
into the mind and the psyche of
shrinivas ramanujan the great
mathematician one of the greatest
mathematicians who ever lived
right
uh he did say that he he gained his
inspiration and his insights his
mathematical insights
because
from from the goddess that he he was
devoted to i think it was goddess nam
giri or whatever the name was i'm not
i'm not personally quite sure of what
the name was but i'm assuming it is nam
giri so he was a very devout hindu
srinivasa
very spiritual person
and he attributed everything that he uh
discovered to to divinity to the goddess
that he uh yeah
so that is what he said now where did
his insides really come from i don't
know
maybe there was a goddess who was
sending his these insides i don't know
about that you know
so
what i would like to say is that there
are many scientists mathematicians etc
the the typical
view about scientists is that they are
atheists scientists don't believe in god
and so on so forth that is not the case
there are many famous scientists who
have made these statements
but it i would say that those people are
would most likely be in a minority
i would say i would imagine that most
scientists
especially the intelligent ones
understand that our understanding of
science is very limited
i'm not trying to say that science is
wrong no science is not wrong but our
understanding of science is very very
superficial in limited because of the
limitations of our intelligence
the human intellect has an upper level
of intelligence beyond which we can't
understand science and therefore our
understanding of the universe is very
very fragmentary very rudimentary and
very limited and therefore there may be
things out there that we can't
understand
and every intelligent reasonably
intelligent scientist knows this and
that's why
such people would be would not consider
themselves to be atheists
i know scientists personally who say
that
human emotions are a bunch of chemical
reactions and all that nonsense i
totally disagree with that i don't know
what human emotions are i i so so that's
my view about this now i don't know what
mr sadhguru has said uh concentrated
energy forms
see he's not a scientist
i would consider i would categorize him
either as somebody who
deals in spirituality or philosophy or
maybe
something in between these two things
so his definition would be different
from the definition that a scientist
would have about energy and all that
concentrated energy is visible it is
measurable
so a god or a goddess is not something
that you can actually see or measure
right
so
maybe it is a certain way of putting
things across that is easily
understandable to the to the lay people
that is not how i would put it across
but uh he is
somebody who has an enormous following a
very accomplished person
so he has his views and uh
maybe maybe i'm much younger than him
and maybe much
less intelligent than him than me so so
so i would refrain from
passing any remarks or comments or
judgment about what he says
but certainly he is a significant force
for positivity in the world which is
always a good thing
so that's what i can say about this
asmita asks what is the reason behind
saudi arabia trying to be progressive
will it
pose any threat from isis
and why did they award shri narendra
modi in the past
okay so saudi arabia is changing now the
their crown prince mohammed bin salman
has essentially
he is now the de facto ruler of the
country
and he is taking the country in a
different direction away from the
traditional
path that it has always been on
uh for the past many many decades
he is modernizing the country
uh
i think now women are allowed to drive
cars and
and do certain things that they were not
allowed to do in the past
and yeah so you could say that the
country is now trying to be more
progressive
and what's the reason for that
the reason i would imagine is because
now the world is changing in the past
the entire world had only one source of
energy of fuel for transportation and
everything else which was oil
and the saudis were the major oil
exporters in the world and therefore
they had a de facto monopoly
on oil exports they were the biggest
exporters so
everybody needed them and therefore they
could afford to do whatever they wanted
within their country and nobody would
would uh you know
interfere
but today things are changing the united
states is now the world's greatest uh
the world's largest producer of of oil
because of shale oil fracking all that
natural gas also is a byproduct of that
and now we are the world is now
uh aware of the problem of climate
change there is a significant sentiment
against using fossil fuels fuels like
oil coal etc
and there is this
deliberate concerted effort
to move towards alternative forms of
energy
so now we have this lithium-ion
batteries that are powering cars and two
wheelers and all that and it's only
going to accelerate
so the world is going to over the next
few decades trying going to try and
move away from burning fossil fuels that
is certainly
on the cards
and therefore saudi arabia is going to
lose its its
central position
globally as the global supplier of
energy for everybody and therefore it's
geopolitical influence and importance is
going to go down and therefore they will
no longer be able to do whatever they
want without worrying about consequences
and that's why
this is a pragmatic move that they are
making they are slowly trying to become
more progressive give more rights to
women so that in the long run
when their
geopolitical situation is less prominent
than it is today they will not have to
face long-term consequences for that
because the western world we know is
very very um
it is very intrusive
right it penalizes countries for having
the wrong lifestyle
when those countries are no longer
useful and so on
so that is the reason why they are doing
this i think it's a pragmatic move will
it pose any threat from isis i don't
know what there is
uh why did they award sri narendra modi
in the past so so the thing is that
india has under mr modi
india has
india has built up
very good relations
with these arabic countries with the
portion girl for the arabic with the
arabic countries
uh
whether it's the uae various emirates in
the uae whether it is oman whether it is
bahrain whether it is the saudi
whether it is saudi arabia india has mr
modi has
managed he has succeeded in developing
very strong very cordial very warm and
friendly relations
with the leaders of these countries
and it's not only about friendship
because in geopolitics like i've said
there is no friendship or enmity there
are only shared
interests
and india is a big major consumer of oil
and maybe there is an understanding that
we will
continue
to be a major consumer of saudi oil
and that's why india is an important
partner for these countries especially
saudi arabia and that's why if somebody
is your important and valuable partner
you will bestow upon them every honor
that you can
bestow
and that's why they are they gave awards
etc to mr modi not just the saudis other
countries as well in the in the persian
gulf region
so that's how it is now if you can if
you contrast that with iran india is no
longer buying
iranian persian oil
not much at any rate the americans have
ensured that india
doesn't
uh buy persian oil because they want to
squeeze the iranian regime and
impose sanctions on them and that's why
you can see now that the relationship
between india and persia is no longer
warm it's no longer very friendly the
way it used to be maybe a decade ago so
that's how it works when your interests
align
you will be very friendly towards each
other you will give each other awards
and treat each other very warmly
when the interests no longer align they
no longer converge when the interest
diverge the relationship will
well no longer be that warm very cold
that cordial that friendly that's how it
works in geopolitics and this is a very
good example of that
okay these are two questions one by
shri's world one by gawang long talk
if you have not read a particular book
till date how can you comment on that
strange
and
you said you didn't read his book but
went on to comment on the book purely
based on not reading the book that's
talked
but other commentaries and summaries of
the book excellent so these are
sarcastic
comments
uh
the book they are referring to i think
it is mr nehru the
what's the book called the discovery of
india
so in one of my previous
sessions in one of the answers of one of
the questions i had said that
i have not read mr book mr nero's book
the discovery of india but
it is a book that is not worth reading
it is garbage or something like that i'd
say like that
and i have got many comments about that
that and i have also commented about
other books by various other people let
me not go into the names
but i have said that i know so and so
person
what his overall ideology was and
therefore i am not interested in reading
so and so chapter or so and so chapter
of the book i have no interest in that
it's a waste of my time the book is of
no
use or no value to me
and
it's a very good question that people
are asking but if you have not read this
book then how can you say the book is
not good how can you comment on that see
it's like this
there are so many books in the world and
there is
a limited amount of time that every
human being has
in this life
and therefore you have to be very
judicious in what you read and how much
and how you invest your time
now when i have
a book that people are saying please
read this you are wrong in your
assessment about this person
read the book and then so on to chapter
so and something is written which will
change your mind
i will not do that
when i know a person
and i know their overall ideology
then i don't need to go into their
tedious
writing
because i know their overall ideology
let's let's say okay let me go into one
name
i had said that i have no interest
in the writings of mr diana saraswati
people have been telling me please read
his book satya prakash chapter this or
chapter that listen i'm not going to do
that it's a waste of my time and let me
tell you why i know overall what mr
diana saraswati's ideology was he was a
social reformer he wanted to reform
hinduism he was against idol worship he
wanted hinduism to give up idol worship
he wanted hinduism to give up
superstitions and various things because
hinduism is backward inferior
it has to be changed
once i know the big picture of this
person i am not going to waste my time
reading
the output
of a mediocre mind
no interest i am sure he must have
written something or the other which is
reasonably good
in one of his chapters i don't care
overall the person was a reformer he is
somebody who believed that hinduism
needs to be reformed once i know that i
have no interest in reading anything
from that person when it comes to
scenario
people say that if you have not read
discovery of india then how can you say
it's bad i know mr nero's intellectual
caliber
then why should i read his book
it's that's how it goes
you have to use
whatever intelligence god the gods have
given you to make these judgments don't
read everything listen it's like this
let me put it in a different way a
slightly cruder way
you don't have to jump into a pile of
garbage to know that it stinks
that's the answer
okay next question it's by said mir taki
ali
in the aryan invasion topic video you
had said that saraswati was wider and
greater than the indus does it mean
longer than the sindhu ii
uh the indus the sindhu river is about
three thousand two hundred kilometers
long and the dry bed of the saraswati
uh from the starting point
till kuch its maximum length is between
two and two and a half thousand
kilometers
so that's the first part of the question
uh no i don't mean to say that the
sindhu or the the saraswati was
necessarily longer
than the sindhu river the indus river
maybe most likely it was not longer
than the sindhu river but it was wider
broader and much more powerful as a
river
so it was
a monsoon fed river
if you look at the sindhu it is
primarily fed by glacial milk melt water
high in the himalayas
if you look at the ganga river it again
originates
from melt water glacial melt water in
the himalayas
if you look at the brahmaputra it does
start off north of the himalayas
from the tibetan plateau from glacial
melt water but more than 80 85 of its
actual volume of water
it acquires this volume of water in
pradesh from monsoons and from rainfall
and all that so
this is a different kind of river it is
a very wide massive river but the
majority of its water again comes from
rainfall
and the rainforest in the arunachal
pradesh region
similarly the saraswati was a monsoon
fed river it was not primarily a glacial
melt water fed river and that's why it
dried out because of climate change
the indian monsoon declined
monotonically from 6000 bc onwards and
eventually it caused the drying up of
the river because there was no longer
enough water
in this riverbed in this enormously wide
riverbed to sustain the course of the
river all the way to the ocean and
that's why it eventually slowly
gradually dried out
therefore i would say that it was most
likely not
as long or longer than the sindhu river
it was probably shorter but it was wider
broader and way more powerful as a river
while it was still in its prime
right so that is the answer of the first
part of the question
now the second question is
why is it called sapta sindhu the region
the punjab uh
region
undivided punjab region why is it called
sindhu why isn't it
saraswati does it mean saraswati was a
tributary of the hindu
that's the second question so the word
sindhu
means river in the sanskrit language
saraswati is the name
is a specific name
it has no other meaning it is the
meaning of one specific river
and one specific goddess the divinity
associated with the driver the goddess
of knowledge
so saraswati has only one meaning it is
a proper noun
it is not a common noun
so if you say the ganga it is a proper
noun but if you say nadi river it is a
common noun right similarly saraswati is
a proper noun it's not a common noun but
sindhu
is a common noun it means river so you
can call
any river a sindhu in sankrit right so
you had seven major rivers
in this region that's why it was called
the sindhu region the region of seven
sindhus or seven rivers
so that's why it was called
subtitle very good question
and lastly the persians were a rigvedic
tribe why didn't they mention the
holiness of the saraswati yamuna ganga
in the religious text
initially originally the parshwa people
who moved to persia they gave the name
their name to this region parshur became
pursue
persia right
initially they were all
adherents or followers of the old
culture old civilization the old
religion if you want to call it that
hinduism
then this prophet came out
emerged zarathustra zoroaster
and he somehow
was very influential and the entire
culture changed
and they adopted his revealed religion
zoroastrianism
which was again a polytheistic religion
it is
labeled as a monotheistic religion which
is completely incorrect now
i don't know what were the priests or
austrian texts in persia we don't have
any these zoroastrian texts are
essentially a revision of the old
religion and culture so many of the
divinities
in
zoroad zoroastrianism
are inverted
so they was become kind of evil
or kind of negative and dhana was or
asuras become kind of positive and so on
and i suppose many of the old divinities
were discarded over time possibly
there is a river called the harahabati
in persia which clearly is named after
the old old great river saraswati
the pronunciation is different becomes
because becomes her in persian in old
persian so saraswati became haravati but
you can see that they named this river
in persia after the great
divine river
of their ancestral lands
yamuna ganga is further east so maybe
they did not
have that much attachment at that point
in time with these rivers but you can
certainly see the the
the desire to
to honor the memory of the great old
river saraswati that is certainly there
so it's all about slowly drifting away
from the ancestral culture and going in
a different direction but you can
certainly see uh
traces strong traces of the origin and
indian culture even today in
zoroastrianism because there are so many
uh aspects of their culture the rituals
the traditions
that closely mirror ancient vedic
culture
for example in vedic culture we had
yagnas
the parsis the zoroastrians they have
yasnas which have the same function and
so on so forth there is so much in
common even today
between these two ancient
traditions
goku says
is it some curse
or is it just bad luck for indians for
the past thousand years i'm not talking
about about invasions but so many
accidents chingas khan did not invade
india and save us from the turks brits
letting gory go back
maharana pratap dying of a hunting
accident shivaji maharaj dying too early
the british defeating the mighty
marathas later we almost got in
independence in 1857.
how netaji was treated did not become
the first pm of india we were too close
to independence too many times but
something unfortunate happened so many
accidents why did it happen only with us
is it a punishment of the gods for
forgetting dharma or is it just bad luck
it's not
punishment from the gods
see it's like this
we make our own luck it's about momentum
when you
are successful
you keep on being successful
when you do something right
you get a positive feedback from the
world because you succeed in whatever
you're trying to do and then that
confidence that positivity
carries forth in the next task that you
take up the next project that you take
up you succeed in that it builds
momentum it keeps on building momentum
so if you are successful you cannot be
successful unless you work very hard and
you work smart as well
so when you do that the gods reward you
with luck
it's not
luck it's just the outcome of
the hard work that you have put in
because that maximizes the chances of
something good happening to you and it
minimizes the chances of something bad
happening to you so it is because of
your hard work your dedication
and
the momentum that this builds that you
become successful and the same thing
also works
when you start failing if you if you
fail at something if you make a big
mistake and
you fail in whatever task or project you
are trying to accomplish
it brings in a feeling of negativity
then you try something else you again
feel it reinforces the feeling of
negativity of defeatism
and it becomes
it it kind of takes on a kind of
momentum and it it's a snowball effect
so success is a snowball effect and
failure is also a snowball effect there
is momentum and success there is
momentum in failure
and what happened in the past 1000 years
is that we kind of slowly slowly at
first but
faster later
built up this momentum of failure
so let's talk about
let's talk about prathiraj jawan he is
not the only person who let muhammad
guri go
before pethira johan it was maharani
niki devi solanki from gujarat who
defeated muhammad gauri in gujarat
and let him escape all the way to
afghanistan
so when you make these mistakes
when one king or queen makes the mistake
it's okay just a few years later another
guy
president johan made the same mistake
he defeated this guy in taran and let
him escape all the way to afghanistan he
could have pursued him and killed him
but he did not do that miracle
i defeated him i am great
so when people start making mistakes one
after the other
it builds momentum in the wrong sense in
the wrong direction negative momentum
and that's what allows your opponents
your enemies to regroup
to understand your tactics because they
have had the experience of your tactics
and then to come back and beat you and
defeat you and once they defeat you
they're not gonna put let their foot off
your throat they're gonna crush you into
the ground
and that's what happened so it was
in the beginning we had powerful kings
and queens who could have
destroyed the threat once and for all
they chose not to do that that led to
the defeat and then that momentum
continued in the wrong direction and we
started experiencing defeat after defeat
initially it took the turks three to
four hundred years to make any inroads
into india they had captured afghanistan
they had
changed the demographics and culture
there they had captured some parts of
western india which is now western
pakistan but they were not able to make
indoors into india because we were so
powerful when we had more unity in those
days but when people started making
mistakes
when people started forgetting the
teachings of great indians like vishnu
tanaka then this became a snowball
effect
and that's how it is now
it is now perceived as bad luck it is
not bad luck it is a series a long chain
of bad decisions one after the other
that built momentum in favor of the
invaders
now
you could say that that shivaji maharaj
reversed that
he
he started the maratha empire he died
too young but his successors were able
to kick out the turks from india and
take over
and reclaim much of india
right the maratha empire at one point in
time uh encompassed most of the indian
subcontinent all the way up to southern
afghanistan
and then again they made the wrong
decisions
wrong succession they made mistakes
which allowed the europeans the british
to take over india in just a couple of
wars in just a few decades
so again mistakes
you if you make mistakes one after the
other it's always a series of mistakes
that creates momentum
so that's what's happened it's not
punishment from the gods it's just that
the momentum built in the wrong
direction it was a series of mistakes
and
then these these ideas got into the
minds of indians these this defeatist
mentality the slave mentality the idea
that white skin is superior
the idea that we are not great warriors
the idea that we have inferior genetics
the questions i get all the time
these
wrong
attitudes and values and beliefs have
crept into the indian mind
and that's where we are today
it's a consequence of all the wrong
decisions that
our leaders our rulers
took over the past 1000 years i would
not attribute it to bad luck
or any punishment from the gods
we make our own luck
if you want the gods to smile at you
work hard and make the right choices the
gods will smile upon you again
so that's where we are today it's the
culmination of 1 000 years of mistakes
and bad choices
it's it all boils down to leadership it
all boils down to leadership it can
always be turned around you just need
one great leader
so that's where we are today
okay this is a interesting question it
is by cute boy
and the question is who are the romani
people
what happened to the romani people in
medieval times in europe
and is eric cantona pashtuni i don't
know what is certainly romani let's
begin who are the romani people the
romani people are a vast
diaspora of indian origin
uh they are a people
who speak
an indo
a so-called indo-aryan language but they
live all across
western eurasia
traditionally now they live all across
the world so they typically were
living
from
the region where they lived let's let's
take a look at the map
let me share my map with you where am i
okay let's go back outwards
so this is eurasia europe in asia
together
so the romani people were typically
found from anatolia turkey
some parts of egypt some parts of iraq
etc
and all across
europe
so these people are of indian origin
they speak in a language that is a
descendant of the old practice of india
the descendant of sanskrit
and it is mixed up with various words
lone words from various
european languages even some turkish
language
so
at least five percent of the population
of turkey is of romani origin
significant populations of romani people
live in eastern europe in romania
serbia bulgaria etc and all other parts
of europe france
spain
northern europe
the united kingdom and so on
so these are
indian origin people what is their
origin and how do they
how did they end up
in europe
so that is a good question how did these
people end up in europe so what happened
so nobody knows for sure what happened
but
what most likely happened is this
during the turkic invasions of india
the turks took
hundreds of thousands of indians as
slaves and transported them to the slave
markets of central asia many many
of these indians died in the himalayas
in the hindu kush mountains hindu kush
means the killer of hindus
so many indians died in the hindukus
mountains because it was too cold
indians were not accustomed to that cold
and then they do not have sufficient
really good clothing for that
but
lacks of indians mostly women and
children but also artisans artists etc
they were transported to the slave
markets of bukhara
samarkand central asia arabia etc
and they were sold off there
and i expect at least
a significant portion of the people of
the arabic and islamic world have some
indian origin as a result
especially from the material matrilineal
lineages
now i think what happened was this
that they also took lots of architects
artists artisans craftsmen musicians etc
to entertain them and to build their
great architecture
and so on in these parts of the islamic
world
and maybe they take maybe they took too
many indians there
and then they realized we have too many
slaves that we don't need now we we
already have enough people who can do
the work for us and there is a surplus
so what do we do with them and they most
likely did not want to massacre them on
their own soil
it's okay to massacre people in india
but not on our own soil so what they
most likely did these turks was to order
these indians
to leave the country but don't go east
back to india go west you are never
allowed to go back to india but go
wander westwards wherever fortune takes
you
and that's what happened
that around a thousand years ago or so
reports began
you have records of these egyptians
coming into europe the europeans thought
of these people as egyptians and that's
what the word gypsy comes from egyptian
egyptian gypsy that way so they thought
they were egyptians they spoke a strange
language which was an indian origin
language and these people they were
never allowed allowed to settle down
anywhere in europe they were persecuted
horribly
there were massacres you could almost
call it a genocide they were enslaved in
europe
but these
people the romani people
they somehow
managed to keep their language alive and
some aspects of their culture alive
so that is the origin of the romani
people they are found all across europe
and the world today
so that is their sad story it is a story
of
incredible hardship terrible persecution
a lot of racism and so on in europe even
today they are marginalized in europe
many of them are stateless people they
don't have any official citizenship
they are not allowed to settle down in
cities they are forced to live on the
outskirts of cities in these caravans
and wagons and all that they don't have
official documentation of any country so
they are still living on the fringes and
margins of society it is outright racism
that you see in europe every day and you
will find that
happening right now as we speak
so let me uh show something
let me see if if you can find evidence
of that
so
this happens even today
so the nazis
the third reich under adolf hitler they
come they committed a horrible genocide
of the romani people they killed
millions of jews but they also killed at
least i would say a million romani
people
and
this persecution happens even today as
you can see these people are living
essentially in a dump yard
they are still marginalized still
persecuted roma persecution intensifies
during the corona virus pandemic in
europe you can see that everywhere even
today
so there is a sad story of the romani
people who have contributed so much to
europe
for instance
spanish culture when you think of
spanish culture you think of flamenco
music and fleming could dance
well flamenco music and flamenco dance
is romani culture it is not spanish
culture it is romani culture they are
the inventors
the creators
of flamenco music and flamenco dance and
there are so many
famous romani people who you may not
know are romani so let me give you some
examples
famous romanis you may have heard of
michael kane
very famous actor well he is of romani
origin have you heard of charlie chaplin
charlie chaplin
charlie chaplin everyone knows him he
was a romani origin his granddaughter
oona chaplin
she is romani she was in the game of
thrones game of thrones very famous
series
you had yul brynner a very famous
hollywood actor who also had russian and
mongol heritage but he was he also had
romani heritage then elvis presley
the very fame one of the most famous
rock singers of all time
he was romani he had roman heritage
pablo picasso
may be the greatest painter of all time
he
uh was a romani person he had indian
heritage
uh
actress rita hayworth
very famous hollywood actress
he was a romani
then
robert plant one of the greatest rock
singers of all time
led zeppelin
he may not look very romani because he
has blonde hair
but
he has romani heritage
uh who else
we had many flamenco singers joaquin
corpus
yes
so he's one of the most famous
flamenco artists dancers in the world
spanish guy i think
and then you had uh
you have people like eric kantuna one of
the greatest footballers of all time
manchester united
he has romani heritage who else do we
have
latan
ibrahimovic everyone knows him
he is romani
andrea pirlo
one of the great greatest italian
footballers of all time
again romani
and so on and so forth there are so many
famous romani people and many of them we
may not even know about because they are
afraid to
to divulge the fact that they are romani
because there is so much persecution
of the romani people there is such a
negative feeling in europe in in the
west about romani people they are looked
upon as criminals as lazy people as
incompetent people and so on all these
terrible stereotypes about them
so they have contributed so much to
europe culturally in in the sports tyson
fury
the heavyweight boxing champion of who's
the boxing champion right now as you
speak
he's also a gypsy and so on and so forth
so that in short is about the romani
people next question
this is by krishnan why didn't the
romans conquer arabia
so let's understand why the romans did
not conquer arabia what is the
point of conquering something see the
romans where
they were colonizing people they were
an imperialistic
people the roman empire
so to understand why they actually
conquered other parts of the world we
have to understand the real motivation
for that the motivation was always very
simple
extraction of gold and wealth and
resources
and food security
they wanted
uh multiple sources of foodstuffs of
food materials
grains cereals fruits
produce livestock and the more territory
you have
more fertile
rich territory you have the the better
your food security is
so these are the reasons why the romans
conquered various parts of the world let
me let's take a look at uh
different way of looking at this
so let's take a look at roman
empire
roads
the roads of the roman empire
so this will give you a good idea
of the
so these are roman roads
if you look at this image here
one second
let me make the image larger
these are roman roads across the
territories they conquer you can see all
across europe
into anatolia and northern northern
africa iberia which is spain and
england as well
so these are roman roads they built this
enormous network of highways and roads
and the purpose of that was very simple
to extract wealth and resources from
roman colonies
why did the british build roads in india
why did the british built railways in
india
this was the infrastructure of
occupation and extraction similarly the
romans did the same thing in all the
territories they conquered they built
these roads as an infrastructure
of occupation and extraction and all of
the wealth and resources was extracted
out of these colonies out of these
conquered territories
and into rome into italy
right
so if you look at all these territories
where the roads are these are rich
fertile lands
rich in terms of mineral resources other
resources gold silver slaves
well populated areas and also for these
are also fertile regions so you could
grow a lot lots of foodstuffs there
harvest things there and all that you
know so that is why the romans conquered
so much territory it was also to
subjugate
any possible
uh
any possible threat to rome so there was
the other other reason but mainly
it was the infrastructure of occupation
now if you look at the arabic peninsula
arabian peninsula
let me share that
so let's take a look at the arabian
peninsula
which is to the east of what the romans
conquered
so tell me something what do you see
here you see an enormous desert here
the population density is always low
even today there in roman times it was
even
less than what it is today
so all these territories the romans
conquered where rich prosperous
and fertile
territories
but the arabian peninsula is just desert
what is the point of conquering a desert
what can you extract out of a desert
nothing grows there
very few people to take as slaves so it
doesn't make any sense
from a
purely logistical perspective from a
colonizer's perspective to conquer
a desert
at that time there was no use for oil
there was no awareness of the fact that
there is so much oil there and the
technology for using oil for energy did
not exist
and therefore it did not make any sense
for the romans to conquer arabia so it's
just a cost versus benefit analysis
there would be a great amount of cost to
send arby's into this desert you would
have to sustain them over hundreds of
kilometers thousands of kilometers
without water without food it would be a
huge logistical effort and what do you
get out of it nothing
so there is no benefit
and there's a great deal of cost and
that's why they did not conquer arabia
that's how
the
psychology
and methodology of conquest works
okay sid asks
why is preserving a culture important
when we can simply embrace science
or we can just follow a particular
culture because it is or do we just
follow a particular culture because it
is simply too attached to our ego so
this is a good question that sid is
asking why do we bother about culture
this is the 21st century why can't we
simply embrace science
and use science for progress and for
uplifting humanity a good question valid
question legitimate question
now let me show you a certain
perspective
let's look at it a different way right
so
once again let me share my screen with
you
let's go to google
let us look at
let's take a look at this
doctors
come under science right
in the 1950s and 1960s
american doctors
used to promote
cigarettes cigarette brands
hundreds of ads
featuring a variety of doctors
these guys were firmly grounded and
rooted in science
the medical profession is a scientific
profession
right and yet
look at this scientific evidence of the
effects of smoking
more doctors smoke camels than any other
cigarette
not one single case of throat irritation
due to smoking so and so brand what
about the lungs they won't talk about
this
so they were using science
to cherry pick data and to mislead the
public and doctors who would have known
about the effects of smoking were very
much complicit in this
activity
so many doctors
so this is what happens when you worship
money
and we do when you don't have any
culture
any cultural moorings that
tell you that this is not a good thing
to do
in the u.s it's always been capitalism
the blind
naked pursuit of money
money is what's worshipped it's not oil
that they worship it's money that the
worship
and that's what happens when there is no
culture and you just blindly follow
science because science can always
be used to mislead people
look at what happened in 2020
we knew about
the transmissibility of the coronavirus
through air
there was data available what did the
who do it suppressed the data
the lab leak theory was pooh-poohed
as
pseudoscience follow the science follow
the science they used to say today it is
one of the
most uh
likely scenarios how the virus escaped
and spread worldwide the lab leak theory
there is so much data that points to it
but because they it was inconvenient for
them they were trying to suppress that
theory now it is a mainstream theory so
what happened overnight what happened to
follow the science
science
is an exact is an exact thing but the
way it is interpreted depends on your
culture your your
the kind of agenda you have and if you
have no moral values if you have no
cultural values then you will use
science to influence people in the wrong
way to to mislead people and to exploit
people
so when you abandon culture
then you open up the doors
for the exploitation of humanity very
often using science as the pretext
and therefore
it is extremely important that we do not
abandon culture and
well which culture that's up to you it's
your personal choice
but i would say that we have seen the
effects of
western culture
abrahamic culture in the destruction of
the
planet in the past three four hundred
years
it is just destroy the planet with
abandon don't worry about the
consequences the earth is a resource to
be exploited
for your benefit for your pleasure for
your enjoyment that is western culture
we know that very well now
so i think it is time for
humanity
to look eastwards
and try out indian culture because
indian culture has never
regarded
the environment as a resource to be
exploited so that is why in short
preserving culture is very important
culture gives you
a moral
framework it gives you certain
principles that you cannot
go against
it gives you certain moral
values that you cannot
transgress upon
and that's what keeps
uh humanity going in the right direction
otherwise just
follow fake science
science is not fake but the
interpretations can be can be falsified
like we just saw american doctors
promoting cigarettes and saying they
were good
that's just one example of thousands
so that's why preserving culture is
important
okay akar says if no information can
travel faster than the speed of light
how does quantum entanglement work
why is the form of theory not scrapped
so quantum entanglement is a qua is a
feature of quantum mechanics but it can
be explained through non-quantum
mechanical examples let's look at it
like this
the thing about entanglement is that
there is no transmission
of information
of any kind in quantum entanglement let
me explain how let's say you have a pair
of gloves a left glove
and the right glove
and you package them separately
you send one of these
packages to a friend of yours in tokyo
and you mail the other package
to a friend of yours in moscow
now when your friend in moscow receives
the package he or she will not know
whether it's a left glove or a right
glove but when he or she will open the
package
they will see what love it is maybe it's
a right love then they will know
instantaneously that your friend in
tokyo received the left glove
and if your friend in tokyo sees the
left glove in the package they will know
immediately that your friend in moscow
received a right-handed glove
now let's say instead of sending
these packages to a friend in moscow and
a friend in
tokyo
you send one package to a friend a
hypothetical friend
who lives
on proxima centauri
and another friend who lives in the
andromeda galaxy
hypothetically it's a thought experiment
now when your friend in the andromeda
galaxy who is one and a half million
light years away from here opens the
package and sees that it's a left-handed
love
he or she or it
will know immediately
that your other friend on proxima
centauri
one and a half million light years away
has received a right-handed glove they
will know instantaneously
that this correlation is there because
they know the correlation exists
but they will not be able to transmit
information
faster than the speed of light so when
they receive one half of the thing they
will know immediately what the other
half is like in the in the other
location so that is quantum entanglement
these two gloves are part of an
entangled system and no matter how far
apart they are once you see one part of
it you will instantaneously know what
the other part is like so let's say you
have a particle
with spin 0
which decays into two particles one with
spin one half and the other with per
spin minus one half
opposite pins and these particles travel
off in different directions let's say
they travel for 10 10 years
almost at the speed of light and then
the one of the particles is measured
and you see it's been minus one half you
will know immediately that the other
particle which is like seven light years
away is of the opposite spin so that is
quantum entanglement you will know
instantaneously what the state of the
other half of the system is but you will
not be able to transmit information
faster than light so there is no actual
transfer of information or data
so
so it is it does not violate
that that part of physics right
so that is the thing about quantum
entanglement it quantum mechanics of
course is non-local there are things
that i will not be able to explain in
great depth because it's so complicated
and it's so confusing but this
hypothetical example should give you an
idea of what quantum
entanglement actually is it is about
a system of particles that is
intrinsically entangled and there is a
correlation between these two particles
no matter where they are located
in the universe so that's what quantum
entanglement is
okay priya asks on mr nehru supporters
claim that if sheree nehru had accepted
the un permanent seat for india then
they would have had to fund the u.n
and at that time india was not in a
position to support even itself
what's your take on this
see
show me one piece of evidence
documentary evidence
that shows that there was a condition
made upon this offer
and the offer was conditional on india
funding the un
there was no condition there was no
string attached to the multiple offers
that mr nero received
there was one offer in 1950 one in 53 or
so and one in 1955. these offers came
from the united states and from the ussr
and on one occasion from both the u.s
and the ussr together please accept a
permanent seat on the un security
council for india and there were no
strings attached if this claim is made
show me the evidence for the claim
there is no evidence because there was
no such string attached there was no
condition imposed upon india that if you
accept this offer then you will have to
spend so and so money every year to fund
the u.n there was no such condition this
is a lie
there's a complete outright fabrication
there is not one piece of documentary
evidence or even anecdotal evidence that
corroborates this claim
look at china mr nehru
ensured that china was eventually given
the seat that was reserved for india
did china fund the u.n
china has spent almost no money
relative relatively speaking in funding
the u.n every country gives some money
to the u.n every year so does india
so does china but if you look at the
funding of the u.n the u.s is the major
funder the u.s is the major source of
funding for the um china's
share of the contribution is quite small
compared to the us even today when china
is like the world's second largest
economy even today their contribution to
the u.n in terms of funding is is very
small compared to the us
and therefore this bears it out that
there was no condition on anybody
that if you are given a permanent seat
on the u.n security council then you
will have to
give so and so amount of funding per
year there was no such deal at all
right
so why did mr neroji
not accept the offer well only mr neroji
can tell to our greatest regret he no
longer is with us
but
that's all i can say about this
okay rohan asks
is time cyclic or linear dharmic
philosophy says time is cyclic whereas
abrahamic religions support the linear
time theory
well
here is the problem when we talk about
about time in physics in science
we are talking about
measurable time time that can be
observed
when you talk about dharmic or abrahamic
philosophies you're talking about
philosophy which is not the same as
science
science is completely separate from
philosophy the philosophical worldview
is completely separate from science
in philosophy
you talk about non-observable
phenomena non-observable effects
you don't need proof of anything in
science you need
science deals with observable
objects and observable phenomena
whatever you talk about in science has
to be observable and measurable
so when we talk about measuring time
we only talk about time that goes in one
direction linear time
the equations of physics are bilinear
they work in both directions you can
even extrapolate back in time and that's
how we came up with the big bang theory
but
there is no evidence from observation
from measurement
that supports
a view
that time is cyclic
show me a single piece of observational
evidence that supports the uh
the hypothesis or theory the time goes
around in cycles
right so according to science
according to physics
time flows in a straight line
and what data do we have we have the
data of the past few hundred years maybe
a few thousand years
that's all it's a very very very small
period of time
for which we have data
the universe is
13.8 billion years old
and the data that we have
is from the past
five ten thousand years at most
right human history
so that is a very very very very small
period of time compared to the actual
age of the universe
so from that i can say that we don't
quite know at what speed time flows
whether it is but the best data that we
have shows that it is linear now when
you talk about philosophy
let's say that we talk about dharmic
philosophy in dharmic philosophy we have
four yogas
right
satya yoga dwapar yogg tritha yoga and
kalyug and then the cycle repeats
it doesn't mean that time starts from
zero again
it means that the same patterns happen
over and over again
but time goes forward
right
so even in the dharmic philosophy which
talks about yugas it says that the same
patterns happen over and over again
it doesn't say that time again goes
backwards starts from zero again it
doesn't ever say that
if you look at hindu cosmology
it says that the age of the universe the
the age of brahma is some
trillion or so years old i'm not sure
what the exact number is
but that also talks about linear time
you have lots of yugas in that you may
have thousands or millions of yugas in
one
lifespan of brahma which is one
lifespan of the universe
so again from that perspective even from
the dharmic perspective you have linear
time yogas are cyclic but those are
patterns that are recurring it doesn't
mean time resets to zero and starts or
every time again from zero
now there are certain scientists
who
in their old age tend to mix up science
and philosophy
and such some such people i heard here
i've been speaking about
various
formats of time
linear time and cyclic time and i don't
know what are the kinds of time i don't
know anything about that maybe i am
maybe my intelligence is much lower than
these people
so maybe i should not comment about them
because maybe they are far more
intelligent than me so all i can say
that from my limited
perspective from my limited intelligence
time only flows in a straight line it's
a linear time even from the dharmic
cosmology
time is linear let's take a look at
dharmic cosmology let's take a look at
that since we have google here
let us take a look at what it looks like
okay let us look at
hindu
cosmology
let's go in there wikipedia
just
for the sake of uh
for convenience hindu cosmology where is
it there has to be some kind of
um
let me take a look at how
time is reckoned
time
into units of time let's take a look at
this
let us
make this larger
so you have
this is the
hindu reckoning of time so one cycle of
brahma is 10 raised to 22 seconds
right 10 raised 22 seconds it's like
trillions or quadrillions of years
that's how long
the age of one universe is
in hindu cosmology in dharmic cosmology
in according to dharmic philosophy
so this is an example of linear time it
is not cyclic time
it does say that after one cycle of
brahma is over a new cycle of brahma
will start which is a new universe so it
talks about a cyclical universe for sure
but in the universe that we live in time
is linear according to this very diagram
here which illustrates the hindu view of
time
and within that you have all the various
yugas and all that which is a different
story which is not really cyclic time it
is just patterns that happen over and
over again but time still flows in a
straight line
so i hope that illustrate that that
that clarifies my view on this there are
people who have spoken about
cyclic time they've even tried to give a
mathematical foundation to that quasi
cyclic time or whatever i have tried to
understand that it i was not able to
understand that most likely i'm not
intelligent enough to understand that so
that's all i can say about that
okay raghav says how can a prime
minister loot our country
how can a prime minister loot our
country
how can a prime minister do corruption
and why has modiji done no corruption
so i know that many people
are in some way detractors of prime
minister modi
but i think
even the biggest detractors and biggest
enemies of mr modi have not been able to
accuse him of corruption
so that is one thing i think we can all
agree upon mr modi has not done any
corruption
he is the one one prime minister that i
can think of personally
who has not done any corruption at all
which makes him unique
the question is how can a prime minister
loot our country
so a prime minister would indulge in
such activities
if they have received the position of
prime minister without going through any
struggle
if a prime minister receives this
position
as a gift
without having to earn it
then they will not value it
right if you receive
see what happens when people win
lotteries they usually go bankrupt in a
few years they waste all the money
because they have not
understood the value of money you
understand the value of money if you
have to struggle for it if you have to
work really really hard to earn every
pesa of it
then you will value the money even if
you have crores of rupees you will not
waste it and you will remain
rich so you value something when you
have to when you have to struggle
hard to earn it
mr modi
to become prime minister he had to
struggle a lot
you may agree or disagree with his
politics
but what is undeniable he has is that he
has put in a lifetime of work
to
to reach a puzzle to reach a position
where he deserves to be the prime
minister of india
did other prime ministers of india in
the past
put in any of that kind of hard work
some prime ministers were actually given
the possession of prime minister as a
gift maybe as an inheritance of their
family or so on
and when people
don't have to work for something they
don't value that thing and that's when
such misuses of of position and power
take place
so i'm not taking any names of course
but that is
how a prime minister would feel that it
is okay for them
to loot the country
okay this is by rajashi searches
the
okay it says please don't underestimate
india's contribution to the i.t sector
we should not forget that many educated
indians go to foreign countries and work
over there so india is a source of
talent i think it's logical to stop
saying india has zero influence my
youtube channel is also observed by
viewers all over the world we indians
are good youtubers too so you should
think a bit positively so what i had
said in one of my previous answers
is that india doesn't have any inflows
in the world geopolitically india
doesn't have an influence in its near
abroad in the indian subcontinent
and india doesn't have any influence
globally
that's what i had said
and this gentleman from his perspectives
feels that i am wrong he says it is
logical to stop saying india has zero
influence because india is a source of
talent for the entire world we send
people brilliant workers in i.t in
software all that technology to foreign
countries very educated people and they
go to other countries and they work over
there so therefore india has influence
okay
so it's like this
these indians
they
they get educated in india
they acquire the knowledge and skills in
india
then they go and settle down in other
countries
they work there
and what do they do there
do they do nation building for india
there
no
what they do
is they work as cheap labor
and they build
the infrastructure
of those countries they build the
facebooks the googles the yahoos the
twitters
they build all the algorithms
and who benefits from these algorithms
from these platforms
it is
the west it is the united states it is
whatever other country they work in and
whose influence increases as a result
it is the geopolitical influence of
these countries that influ increases as
a result are indians respected
in the
west well they are not disrespected per
se
but
what influence do they have over there
does the united states
regard hinduism
as something good or positive
not at all
hinduism is denigrated as something
backward in the u.s there is so much
hindu phobia in every u.s university and
there is
not a single repercussion
for saying bad things about hinduism and
for being hindu phobic but if you say
something similar to for another
religion
you are cancelled and you have to
apologize
so where is the influence for india
what are you talking about
just because we send our cheap labor to
work
in other countries and build their
infrastructure doesn't mean we have any
influence
in the 1970s 80s etc
cheap indian labor went to the gulf and
they built these giant cities like dubai
and abu dhabi and all that
does it mean that india has influence
there
they see indians as workers
as coolies
you call that influence
so today we have cyber coolies
that's all indians are looked upon as
in the west
india's influence will grow when we
start creating our own platforms our own
cyber infrastructure our own virtual
universe
that's when india will be respected and
that's when india will have influence
so
so therefore i have to disagree with
what this gentleman is saying and
disagree very strongly
that's not what influence is
okay we are almost at the two hour mark
let me take one more question
this is by raghav
sir am i the body or the mind
the good old mind body problem so it's
essentially about consciousness
we know that we are conscious
and our consciousness seems to be in
this region because our sensory organs
are in this region but
are we the body or are we something
separate from the body the mind or is
the mind also something that's part of
the body that is the philosophical
question you're asking because it is not
a scientific question science is unable
to deal with these questions science as
of today is not equipped to deal with
these questions
but i would say that we are not the body
the body is
simply an animal that you ride think
about a horse rider
the horse rider goes everywhere on the
horse but he is not the horse or she is
not the horse
similarly the body that we have
is essential to our existence
but it is simply an animal
that we ride
right the consciousness the chitta is
something else
does it emerge out of the complexity of
the neurons in our brain
maybe maybe not there is no evidence
that it does there is no evidence that
it does not but what i can say for sure
is that the body even though
we regard the body as
a
as an extension of ourselves our entire
self image
is intrinsically tied to our body and
yet the body is not who we really are
the body is simply a vehicle it's simply
an animal under our care we have to take
care of this animal
if we take care of it well it will last
us for a very long time if we
don't take care of it and if we
abuse it
then we will not exist for very long on
this on in this world
but
what the real consciousness is what the
self is
is certainly not the body it is
something deeper maybe it is
something that emerges out of the
complexity of the brain or maybe it is
something else entirely there are
certain philosophical schools of thought
that say that consciousness permeates
the entire universe it concentrates in
some locations like in
like in the human body in the human
brain but maybe it's not that something
that emerges out of the brain maybe it's
something that localizes temporarily in
the brain and maybe it transcends human
existence
maybe
so that's
what philosophy and spirituality says
but science doesn't have any answers as
of today
so i would certainly say that you are
not the body
you are the mind but where does the mind
reside and where does it emerge from
is something that we still don't know
for sure of course our ancient
traditions are very clear about that
if you look at
the dharmic traditions it's very clear
that the soul the atma
is something that permeates the entire
universe there is a universal soul
and
our soul is just a
localized representation of something
much bigger so that is the
philosophical and spiritual
dharmic
outlook or world view science is unable
to answer any of these questions as of
today
so that
is what i can say about this in very
brief so my friends this brings us to
the end of today's session it's almost
two hours i think it's the longest
session i've done thus far so thank you
so much for all your questions i had
many more questions lined up but i have
run out of time
so i will keep on doing this you are
asking such brilliant questions thank
you so much for that i really appreciate
it i would like to thank all of the
people
who have
asked me questions all of the
subscribers all of the members all of
those you of you who are supporting the
channel in various means thank you so
much for it i am very very grateful
and i will see you tomorrow tomorrow is
a live chat q a session so i will see
you then until then take care and bye